let set19 =
    [
        {
            question: `#1. Which of the following statements is not correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Like charges attract each other.',
                    'B. Electric charge obtained by rubbing materials against each other is static.',
                    'C. Electricity is generated by the movement of charge.',
                    'D. The charge from any charged object is sent to the earth by earthing.',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Like charges repel each other, while unlike charges attract each other.Charge is generated by rubbing objects against each other. It is a convention to call the charge acquired by a glass rod when it is rubbed with silk as positive. The other kind of charge is called negative.When charge moves, electricity is generated.The process of sending the extra charge from a charged object is called earthing.`
        },
        {
            question: `#2. Consider the following statements regarding lightning: \n 1. Positive charge accumulated near the surface of the earth and the negative charge accumulated at the lower surface of the clouds combine to generate light and sound of lightning. \n 2. The process of generation of lightning is called electric discharge. This can occur between two or more clouds; or between the clouds and earth. \n 3. To protect the buildings from lightning, an object called lightning conductor is used. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 2 and 3 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: During the development of a thunderstorm, the air currents move upward while the water droplets move downward. These vigorous movements cause separation of charges. By a process, the positive charges collect near the upper edges of the clouds and the negative charges accumulate near the lower edges. There is accumulation of positive charges near the ground also. When the magnitude of the accumulated charges becomes very large, the air which is normally a poor conductor of electricity, is no longer able to resist their flow. Negative and positive charges meet, producing streaks of bright light and sound. We see streaks as lightning . The process of generation of lightning is called electric discharge. This can occur between two or more clouds; or between the clouds and earth. Lightning Conductor is a device used to protect buildings from the effect of lightning. A metallic rod, taller than the building, is installed in the walls of the building during its construction. One end of the rod is kept out in the air and the other is buried deep in the ground. The rod provides easy route for the transfer of electric charge to the ground.`
        },
        {
            question: `#3. The earth is divided into many layers. Which of the following layers is responsible for tremors?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Crust',
                    'B. Mantle',
                    'C. Outer core',
                    'D. Inner core',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Faults in the outermost layer of earth cause tremors. This layer is called ‘crust’. The outermost layer of the earth is not in one piece. It is fragmented. Each fragment is called a plate. These plates are in continual motion. When they brush past one another, or one plate goes under another due to collision, they cause disturbance in the earth’s crust. It is this disturbance that shows up as an earthquake on the surface of the earth.,  The tremors produce waves on the surface of the earth. These are called seismic waves. The waves are recorded by an instrument called the seismograph.`
        },
        {
            question: `#4. Consider the following statements about earthquakes: \n 1. Earthquakes are caused by the movement of plates, the boundaries of the plates are the weak zones where earthquakes are more likely to occur. The weak zones are also known as seismic or fault zones. \n 2. In India, the areas most threatened are Kashmir, Western and Central Himalayas, the whole of North-East, Rann of Kutch, Rajasthan and the Indo - Gangetic Plain. Some areas of South India also fall in the danger zone. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. None of the above',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Earthquakes arise due to the movement of plates. The boundaries of the plates are the weak zones where earthquakes are more likely to occur. The weak zones are also known as seismic or fault zones.In India, the areas most threatened are Kashmir, Western and Central Himalayas, the whole of North-East, Rann of Kutch, Rajasthan and the Indo - Gangetic Plain. Some areas of South India also fall in the danger zone.`
        },
        {
            question: `#5. Consider the following statements regarding the measurement of the magnitude of earthquake. \n 1. The power of an earthquake is expressed in terms of a magnitude on a scale called Richter scale. \n 2. Richter scale is a linear scale. \n 3. An increase of 2 in magnitude means 1000 times more destructive energy. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 1 and 3 only',
                    'C. 2 and 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: The power of an earthquake is expressed in terms of a magnitude on a scale called Richter scale. Richter scale is not linear. It is logarithmic. As it is logarithmic, each measurement from 1 to 10, marked on the Richter scale denotes a ten times amplitude and 32 times the energy on the seismograph. In fact, an increase of 2 in magnitude means 1000 times more destructive energy.`
        },
        {
            question: `#6. Consider the following statements: \n 1. Emission of light by objects. \n 2. Reflection of light by objects. \n 3. Dispersion of light. \n Which of the above is/are related to the phenomenon of seeing objects?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 1 and 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: To be able to see an object, it is necessary for light from the object to reach the eyes. This light can reach the eyes through emission or reflection.Objects which emit light of their own are called luminous objects, while objects which do not emit light are called non luminous.The phenomenon of splitting of white light into,  its constituent colours is called dispersion. Rainbow is a natural phenomenon caused by dispersion of light. Dispersion is not responsible for the sight of objects.`
        },
        {
            question: `#7. Which of the following parts of the eye is responsible for its characteristic color?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Lens',
                    'B. Cornea',
                    'C. Retina',
                    'D. Iris',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Iris is the part of the eye which is responsible for its characteristic colour. The eye has a roughly spherical shape. Outer coat of the eye is white. It is tough so that it can protect the interior of the eye from accidents. Its transparent front part is called cornea. Behind the cornea, we find a dark muscular structure called iris. In the iris, there is a small opening called the pupil. The size of the pupil is controlled by the iris. Behind the pupil of the eye is a lens which is thicker in the centre, called the convex lens. The lens focuses light on the back of the eye, on a layer called retina.`
        },
        {
            question: `#8. Consider the following statements about retina: \n 1. Retina contains several nerve cells.,  \n 2. The blind spot is present at the junction of the optic nerve and the retina. \n 3. The impression of an image does not vanish immediately from the retina. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Retina contains several nerve cells. Sensations felt by the nerve cells are then transmitted to the brain through the optic nerve. There are two kinds of cells (i) cones, which are sensitive to bright light and (ii) rods, which are sensitive to dim light.At the junction of the optic nerve and the retina, there are no sensory cells, so no vision is possible at that spot. This is called the blind spot. The impression of an image does not vanish immediately from the retina. It persists there for about 1/16th of a second. So, if still images of a moving object are flashed on the eye at a rate faster than 16 per second, then the eye perceives this object as moving., `
        },
        {
            question: `#9. Which of the following is the Braille system associated with?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Laws of reflection of light',
                    'B. People with near and far sightedness',
                    'C. Visually challenged people',
                    'D. None of the above',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: The most popular reading and writing system for visually challenged persons is known as Braille. Louis Braille, himself a visually challenged person, developed a system for visually challenged persons and published it in 1821. Braille system has 63 dot patterns or characters.`
        },
        {
            question: `#10. Animals have eyes shaped in different ways, and have various specialities. Consider the following statements regarding these specialities: \n 1. Eyes of a crab are quite small but they enable the crab to look all around him. \n 2. Butterfly has large eyes that seem to be made up of thousands of little eyes. \n 3. The Owl has a large cornea and a large pupil to allow more light in its eye. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 2 and 3 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Eyes of a crab are quite small but they enable the crab to look all around him. Butterfly has large eyes that seem to be made up of thousands of little eyes. It can see not only the front and the sides but back as well.The owl has a large cornea and a large pupil to allow more light in its eye. Owl can see very well in the night but not during the day. Also, it has on its retina a large number of rods and only a few cones. The day birds on the other hand, have more cones and fewer rods.`
        }
    ]